Dance Program Records UA165
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Dance Program Records
1955 -- 2012
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Drama and Dance
Department of Physical Education
UA165
6.5 Linear Feet 6 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series: History and development; Course materials and syllabi; Programming and publicity; Student organizations; and Unprocessed accessions.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains audiovisual material, course materials, newspaper clippings, photographs, publications, and subject files related to the Dance Program, which is currently part of the Department of Drama and Dance. This program was formerly associated with the Department of Physical Education. The professionals records of Professor Alice Trexler, former director of the Dance Program, can be found in the "Unprocessed accessions" series.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of Drama and Dance formally came into existence on September 1, 1983. The Department of Drama absorbed the Dance Program which had been part of the Department of Physical Education to create the newly formed department. Professor Sherwood Collins, who had been the Chair of the Department of Drama remained as the head of the newly expanded department. Associate Professor Alice Trexler, who had been at the helm of the Dance Program, remained as its director after the formation of the new department had been officially completed.
The Department of Drama and Dance articulated information about the Department in the Bulletin of Tuft University for the academic year 1984-1985 as follows, "Through the study of drama and theater arts, the student can cultivate an understanding and appreciation of one of Western society's main civilizing forces; develop powers of intellect, imagination, emotion, and vocal and bodily expressiveness, as well as standards of good taste and workmanship; and gain a sound foundation for later pursuit of interests in this field". Regarding the Dance Program, the Bulletin stated, "The objectives of the Tufts dance program are to acquaint the student with both dance technique and dance theory within the realm of a liberal arts education".
The Department of Drama and Dance offers graduate programs leading to a Master of Arts as well as a Doctor of Philosophy.
Dance is a component of the Department of Drama and Dance, operating within the liberal arts philosophy with beginning to advanced courses. Events vary by semester, including informal presentations of faculty/student/guest work. Creativity and critical thinking are stressed in classes. The program serves the liberal arts goals rather than having a conservatory orientation even though several or more of our courses offer opportunities for students to continue with advanced skills. Modern dance is the core curricular element along with several non-western forms offered during the year.
Conditions Governing Access
University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs; Student Activities -- Performing Arts; Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material
- History and development, 1970 -- 2004; UA165.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of files related to the history, development and underlying philosophy of the Dance Program. Files include information related to the Program when it was associated with the Department of Physical Education as well as its time with the Department of Drama. Materials related to program requirements, as well as awards and honorary degree recipients, are also included.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Dance Program, 1970 -- 1974; UA165.001.001.00001 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance Program, 1975 -- 1979; UA165.001.001.00002 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance Program, 1980 -- 1985; UA165.001.001.00003 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance and the Arts requirement, 1981; UA165.001.001.00004 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Plaudit Award Chellis, 1982; UA165.001.001.00005 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dunham Honorary Degree, 1986; UA165.001.001.00006 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance Program certificate program docs, 1986 -- 1992; UA165.001.001.00007 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance Program, 1986 -- 1989; UA165.001.001.00008 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance Program, 1990 -- 1994; UA165.001.001.00009 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance Program, 1995 -- 1999; UA165.001.001.00010 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance Program, 2000 -- 2004; UA165.001.001.00011 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
- Course materials and syllabi, 1970 -- 1992; UA165.002; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This collection includes course planning materials, syllabi and a thesis related to the Dance Program.
  - 70s Syllabi (Dittos), 1970 -- 1979; UA165.002.001.00012 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Tufts 70's and past courses, 1970 -- 1979; UA165.002.001.00013 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Beckwith Ditto Masters, 1977 -- 1983; UA165.002.001.00014 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Labanotation AT, 1979; UA165.002.001.00015 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Course Information, 1979 -- 1990; UA165.002.001.00016 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - PJF Modern I and II 054, 1979; UA165.002.001.00017 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 70 Perspectives of Dance, 1979 -- 1986; UA165.002.001.00018 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Syllabi, 1980 -- 1991; UA165.002.001.00019 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Faulkner ditto masters, 1980; UA165.002.001.00020 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Special Topics - AT ditto masters PCA, 1980; UA165.002.001.00021 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Modern IV AT, 1980 -- 1985; UA165.002.001.00022 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - File 13 92A Laban Theory, 1980 -- 1985; UA165.002.001.00023 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Modern II, 1982; UA165.002.001.00024 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Josa-Jones Mod I, 1983; UA165.002.001.00025 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Modern III AT, 1983; UA165.002.001.00026 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - DNC56 Mod IV AT, 1983; UA165.002.001.00027 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 117 Studies in Dance Composition, 1984 -- 1991; UA165.002.001.00028 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 124 Aesthetics/criticism, 1986; UA165.002.001.00029 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 57 Ballet II, 1986 -- 1990; UA165.002.001.00030 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Minors Thesis in Dance Eric Siegel, 1986; UA165.002.001.00031 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Tufts Summer Dance, 1986 -- 1988; UA165.002.001.00032 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Summer School Laban and West African, 1987 -- 1992; UA165.002.001.00033 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 55. Modern Dance III, 1987 -- 1989; UA165.002.001.00034 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 110. History of Dance, 1988 -- 1991; UA165.002.001.00035 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Course offerings - Experimental College Syllabi, 1989 -- 1990; UA165.002.001.00036 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 86. Dance Therapy, 1989 -- 1991; UA165.002.001.00037 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - 117. Studies in Dance Composition, 1989 -- 1991; UA165.002.001.00038 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - DT DN86 Syllabi, 1992; UA165.002.001.00039 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
- Programming and publicity, 1958 -- 2005; UA165.003; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains clippings, flyers, programs, posters and other materials related to events and program sponsored by the Drama Department.
  - Evening of Dance program and script, 1958; UA165.003.001.00041 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Jackson Dance Group Annual Spring Concert Poster, 1964; UA165.003.001.00042 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Programs and flyers, 1970 -- 1971; UA165.003.001.00043 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and flyers, 1971 -- 1972; UA165.003.001.00044 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1973 -- 1974; UA165.003.001.00045 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1975 -- 1976; UA165.003.001.00046 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1976 -- 1977; UA165.003.001.00047 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1977 -- 1978; UA165.003.001.00048 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1978 -- 1979; UA165.003.001.00049 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Additional dance publicity, 1978 -- 1996; UA165.003.001.00050 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1979 -- 1980; UA165.003.001.00051 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Dance program faculty news clips and articles, 1979 -- 1986; UA165.003.001.00052 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1980 -- 1981; UA165.003.001.00053 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1981 -- 1982; UA165.003.001.00054 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1982 -- 1983; UA165.003.001.00055 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity pieces, 1982 -- 1984; UA165.003.001.00056 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs, 1983 -- 1984; UA165.003.001.00057 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Publicity and programs (2), 1983 -- 1984; UA165.003.001.00058 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Concert programs and publicity materials, 1983 -- 2003; UA165.003.001.00059 (Box UA165 Shared 1)
  - Concert Harry Correspondence DNC as Lib A F83, 1983; UA165.003.002.00001 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - DNC as Lib A F83, 1983; UA165.003.002.00002 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity F83 Dance as a Liberal Art event, 1983; UA165.003.002.00003 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Copy Publicity Fall 83 DNC as Lib A and Announce of new Dept Affiliation, 1983; UA165.003.002.00004 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - DNC as a Liberal Art/Financial F83, 1983; UA165.003.002.00005 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs Fall-Spring, 1984 -- 1985; UA165.003.002.00006 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1985 -- 1986; UA165.003.002.00007 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1986 -- 1987; UA165.003.002.00008 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1987 -- 1988; UA165.003.002.00009 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1988 -- 1989; UA165.003.002.00010 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1989 -- 1990; UA165.003.002.00011 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1990 -- 1991; UA165.003.002.00012 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1991 -- 1992; UA165.003.002.00013 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1992 -- 1993; UA165.003.002.00014 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1993 -- 1994; UA165.003.002.00015 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Lib Exhibit: DNC as Lib A and research Fall, 1993; UA165.003.002.00016 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1994 -- 1995; UA165.003.002.00017 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 1995 -- 1996; UA165.003.002.00018 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs (2), 1995 -- 1996; UA165.003.002.00019 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Office archives, 1996 -- 1997; UA165.003.002.00020 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Dance Info, 1997 -- 1998; UA165.003.002.00021 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs Spring, 1998; UA165.003.002.00022 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Tufts Dance Program Fall-Spring, 1998 -- 1999; UA165.003.002.00023 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Postings, 1999 -- 2000; UA165.003.002.00024 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Fall - Spring, Originals, 2000 -- 2001; UA165.003.002.00025 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Spring 2001 performances, UA165.003.002.00026 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Dance Program Info, 2001 -- 2002; UA165.003.002.00027 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Dance Program Info, 2002 -- 2003; UA165.003.002.00028 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - F02-S04 Curr/Perf Publicity, 2002 -- 2004; UA165.003.002.00029 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity and programs, 2003 -- 2004; UA165.003.002.00030 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Publicity Fall - Spring, 2004 -- 2005; UA165.003.002.00031 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
- Student organizations, 1971 -- 1986; UA165.004; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains materials related to student run organizations that supported the activities and programming conducted by the Drama Program. These organizations include the Dance Advisory Board and its successor organization, the Dance Collective.
  - Student Dance records, 1971 -- 1973; UA165.004.002.00032 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Dance Advisory Board 1976-77 Dance Touring Program, 1976 -- 1977; UA165.004.002.00033 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - DNC Advisory Board, 1977 -- 1978; UA165.004.002.00034 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - DNC Advisory Board, 1976 -- 1979; UA165.004.002.00035 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - T.D.C., 1978 -- 1979; UA165.004.002.00036 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
  - Tufts Dance Collective, 1980 -- 1986; UA165.004.002.00037 (Box UA165 Shared 2)
- Additional accessions, UA165.000103
  - Alice Trexler Personal Archive Box, 1967 -- 2012; UA165-001 (Box data_value_missing_168a1eeea45b93b5abf62e8cad21a8ee, Box 1)
  - Dance Program - Curriculum/History/Artistic Development, 1955 -- 2012; UA165-002 (Box data_value_missing_8bc926e10e4b91547bade068beb1ccc6, Box 2)
  - Videos, 2000 -- 2010; UA165-003 (Box data_value_missing_91332e211ffbc3721ad55546d758fed1, Box 3)
  - UMatic tapes, 1970 -- 2000; UA165-004 (Box data_value_missing_9b9ab7b011f53adeb75397367bf42b51, Box 4)